Finding Aid for Communicative Disorders Clinic (University of Michigan) Records 1905-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Communicative Disorders Clinic (University of Michigan) records 1905-1999, 1934-1990
University Michigan. Communicative Disorders Clinic.
2 linear feet
9674 Bimu 2
The University of Michigan's Communicative Disorders Clinic was one of the first programs in communications disorders in the United States. The clinic administers a wide range of speech-language and audiology services to children and adults. One program of the clinic was the Shady Trails Camp, a summer overnight camp for youths suffering from a range of communications disorders which had been started in 1932 by John Clancy. The records are predominantly administrative files of the Communicative Disorders Clinic and of Shady Trails Camp and are divided into two series: Administrative File and Shady Trails Camp. Includes photographs of Shady Trails campers, staff and activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Communicative Disorders Clinic in 1996 and 1997 (Donor # 8473 ).
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted to protect individual privacy. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws.
The following are terms of restriction for specific genres of records found in this record group:
patient/client records are restricted for one-hundred years from date of creation.
The record group University of Michigan Communicative Disorders Clinic contains restricted files; these files have been removed to the vault.
The Communicative Disorders Clinic of the University of Michigan was established in 1936 as one of the first programs in communications disorders in the United States. The clinic possesses a long tradition of providing excellent diagnostic and therapy programs to individuals with communication impairments. The clinic administers three program services with professional staff dedicated to each. Outpatient Services offers a full range of speech-language and audiology services to both children and adults. The Aphasia Service includes Residential Aphasia Service where adults with aphasia attend six-week sessions throughout the year, and "Opening Doors," a two-day seminar dealing with quality of life issues for sufferers of aphasia.
The third service of the clinic was the Shady Trails Camp, a summer overnight camp for youths suffering from a range of communications disorders. It was founded in 1932 by John Clancy as the National Speech Improvement Camp, with an idea to provide a space for children with speech handicaps to develop their communications skills as well as outdoor skills and other character traits normally associated with summer camps. The first season had four campers and the camp took place in a hotel, which Clancy leased. Through the next dozen years, camp enrollment steadily increased to 60 students in 1944, when Clancy began a building fund drive to construct a new camp. Construction of the Shady Trails Camp was completed in 1947 on the shores of the Grand Traverse Bay, just south of Northport, Michigan.
From its inception in 1932, the camp enjoyed informal association with the University of Michigan, with faculty members serving on the camp staff. In 1949, Shady Trails Camp was acquired by the university through a gift of the Kresge Foundation. The formal affiliation with the university resulted in an expanded program with faculty from the fields of education, medicine, dentistry, psychology, speech pathology, and audiology working with the camp as clinicians. Through the university affiliation, the Camp also expanded its graduate student intern program where as associate clinicians, students were able to gain valuable professional experience.
Enrollment in the Shady Trails Camp had neared 120 campers in 1993. The camp was forced to close its doors in 1995 due to financial troubles brought about by cuts in funding from the State. The Communicative Disorders Clinic continues to serve the clientele of the Shady Trails Camp.
The records of the Communicative Disorders Clinic are predominantly administrative files of the clinic and of Shady Trails Camp. The record group came to the archives in two accessions. The material received in 1996 is in the Administrative Files series. A second series, Shady Trails Camp Files, was created from the material received in 1997. A small amount of material from the 1996 accession was interfiled into the Shady Trails Camp Files series.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Communicative Disorders Clinic.; Shady Trails Camp (Northport, Mich.); Clancy, John Newman.; National Speech Improvement Camp.; Communicative disorders in children.; Communicative disorders in adolescence.; Camps--Michigan--Northport.; Communicative disorders--Education.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Communicative Disorders Clinic.; Communicative disorders in children.; Communicative disorders in adolescence.; Camps--Michigan--Northport.; Communicative disorders--Education.; Shady Trails Camp (Northport, Mich.); National Speech Improvement Camp.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative Files
  The two main subseries of the Administrative Files, Budgets and Development Correspondence, provide the most notable records in this series. Budgets provides information on the Clinic's financial operations from 1989 to 1995. Correspondence deals almost exclusively with external fundraising for the Clinic and is organized by the individuals solicited. The bulk of these records are from 1990 to 1995.
  - Administrative Team Minutes 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - Americans With Disabilities Act Information 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Budgets
    - 1989-1990 Request (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 Internal (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 Request (Box 1)
    - 1992-1993 Request (Box 1)
    - 1992-1993 Operating Account (Box 1)
    - 1993-1994 Financial Plan (Box 1)
    - 1994-1995 Financial Plan (Box 1)
    - 1994-1995 Request (Box 1)
    - 1995-1996 Operating Account (Box 1)
    - 1995-1996 Request (Box 1)
    - 1992-1996 Four Year Financial Plan (Box 1)
  - Development Correspondence
    - Solicited Non-Donors (Box 1)
    - Dronet, E.J. 1995 (Box 1)
    - Herrod, Tom 1993 (Box 1)
    - Martinez, Elena 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - Monaghan, Thomas 1995 (Box 1)
    - Navetta, Mike and Donna 1994 (Box 1)
    - Parker, Ivan 1992-1995 (Box 1)
    - Peticolas, Barry 1991-1995 (Box 1)
    - Pitts, Bill 1995 (Box 1)
    - Severt, Martha 1994 (Box 1)
    - Stone, Jim 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Vice President for Academic Affairs 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Marketing Donations 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Support Procedures 1993-1995 (Box 1)
- Shady Trails Camp
  The Shady Trails Camp series contains documentation on the University of Michigan affiliated speech improvement camp operated near Northport, Michigan. The series spans the years from 1905 to 1993 and is divided into two subseries: Administrative Files, and Visual Materials. The Administrative Files subseries contains a variety of material including annual reports, camp policies, clippings, correspondence, deeds (1905-1949) histories, staff training materials and other information concerning the operation of the camp. The Visual Material subseries consists of nearly 1 foot of material including, photographic prints, slides, and some negatives. Photographs date from 1934 to 1993 and consist of group and individual photos of campers and staff, the Clancy family, as well as photos of activities, facilities, and local scenery. A large number of undated photographs are sorted by most probable decade. This series also includes some slides dating from 1959 to 1985. A small collection of undated negatives is also included.
  - Administrative Files
    - Annual Reports 1942, 1943, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Application Forms 1978-1983 (Box 1)
    - Camp Survey (UM Facilities Planning) 1992 (Box 1)
    - Camp Deeds 1905-1949 (Box 1)
    - Camp Inspections 1980-1984 (Box 1)
    - Camp Investigations 1983, 1992-1994, 3 folders
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2094 ]
    - Camp Maps and Floor Plans 1956-1980 (Box 1)
    - Camp Policies and Disaster Plans (Box 1)
    - Case Files 1940, 1946-1954, 2 folders
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2054 ]
    - Correspondence
      - General 1934-1968 (Box 1)
      - Anderson, George and Lyn 1993-1994 (Box 1)
      - Fitch, Roger 1993-1995 (Box 1)
      - Hagerman, Marie Clancy 1993-1995 (Box 1)
      - Huetwell, Frederick 1992-1995 (Box 1)
      - Jones, James Earl 1994 (Box 1)
      - Kalfaian, Mark 1994 (Box 1)
      - Kurtz, Robert M. 1994 (Box 1)
      - Morgan, Norm 1993 (Box 1)
      - Rubin, Richard I. 1993-1994 (Box 1)
      - Sandon, Dory 1993-1994 (Box 1)
      - Slack, Robert 1994 (Box 1)
      - Warm, David and Paula 1993-1995 (Box 1)
      - Winans, Paul 1993 (Box 1)
      - Wright, Simon 1993 (Box 1)
      - Youth Foundation of America 1989-1994 (Box 1)
      - Ziegler, Alken 1993 (Box 1)
    - Recreation Coordinator Manual (Box 1)
    - Reports
      - Miscellaneous (Including Audit Report, Expansion Needs, Progress Report) 1954-1978 (scattered) (Box 1)
      - An Evaluation of Rehabilitation Techniques Used in the Speech Camp, by Orpha L. Nale 1943 (Box 1)
      - History and Operations of Shady Trails, University of Michigan Speech Improvement Camp by Gene Walle, [ca. 1956] (Box 1)
    - "Snipe" Cards and Drawings 1939-1948 (Box 1)
    - Staff Manual 1987 (Box 1)
    - Staff Meeting Minutes 1990
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2090 ]
    - Staff Memos 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - Staff Orientation 1991 (Box 1)
    - Therapy Aids (Box 1)
  - Visual Materials
    - Photographs
      - 1934-1938 (Box 2)
      - 1940-1942 (Box 2)
      - 1944-1946 (Box 2)
      - 1948-1950 (Box 2)
      - 1951 (Box 2)
      - 1952-1953 (Box 2)
      - 1954-1956 (Box 2)
      - 1957-1960 (Box 2)
      - 1961-1964 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1969 (Box 2)
      - 1970-1973 (Box 2)
      - 1976-1979 (Box 2)
      - 1985-1993 (Box 2)
      - Undated, [1930s ?] (Box 2)
      - Undated, [1940s ?] (Box 2)
      - Undated, [1950s ?] (Box 2)
      - Undated, [1960s ?] (Box 2)
      - Undated, [1970s ?] (Box 2)
      - Undated, [1980s ?] (Box 2)
      - Undated, [1990s ?] (Box 2)
    - Negatives undated (Box 2)
    - Slides
      - 1959-1966 (Box 2)
      - 1971 (Box 2)
      - 1972 (Box 2)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - 1976-1978 (Box 2)
      - 1981-1985 (Box 2)